Can you talk about using HCG only to
restore fertility when FSH is cost
prohibitive? Yeah. So, uh, Dave came to
town recently and we had some discussion
on this topic because there's there's a
lot of talk in, um, the forums and on
some of your other videos about the use
of both hCG and FSH for the return of
fertility when you're on testosterone
therapy. But here in the states, FSH is
both extremely expensive and it's kind
of difficult to actually even prescribe
or get because it's um classified as a
biologic. So, it is not something that I
have access to easily prescribe to
patients and um I don't use it in my my
practice at all. So, when we have
someone on testosterone that desires to
get their sperm count back up, we use
hCG by itself. Um, one thing to note is
I think there's a lot of um, misstep
from patients on following up to check
sperm analyses. So, you know, I think
guys are told from a young age don't get
people pregnant and then they think in
their head that they can get people
pregnant very easily and then they fail
to understand that it's more difficult
than it really is. So, when they're on
testosterone, they think it's just going
to be really easy. They'll get on hCG
and everything will be fine. And
sometimes it is um and even very low
dosing of hCG I've seen have some um
like you know they return to normal very
quickly versus some people do need
higher dosing of it. Um but really you
don't know what dose a person needs
unless you recheck a sperm analysis. Um
even hCG has some you know not low cost
associated with it. It's going to be
lower than taking the combination of hCG
and FSH for sure. Um, but you know, some
people just start a very high dose out
the gate to get that sperm count back up
as quickly as possible. And that needs
to, I think, be decided more based off
of how long has the patient been on
testosterone, what is their age
currently, and how quickly are they
trying to get things back to where they
were. Um, also if they don't know if
they've uh had low tes uh low sperm
count to begin with, that's something to
to consider too because um if they had a
baseline sperm analysis that showed they
already were abnormal, then they're
going to probably need some additional
support. Um, but the dosing that, you
know, the lowest dosing that I've seen
used, um, both in studies and in my
practice, 500 units twice weekly. I've
seen some guys get back to completely
normal sperm counts and have no problem
conceiving on. Um, most the studies I
think more support at least three times
a week or every other day dosing. Um,
but again, you can kind of see what how
the if if you have a little bit of time,
you can start kind of low and then
recheck sperm analysis and increase from
there because we know some guys just
won't feel well on hCG. And um, just
adding a lot more of that in all at once
might not be the best approach depending
on the person.
>> How long would it take? was the timeline
when you inject
HCG before your sperm count is enough to
impregnate
the wife.
>> Good question. So I mean theoretically
testosterone might not cause um
aospermia in the first place. So some
guys get pregnant without even taking
hCG um or their wives do I should say.
Um so you know the if they are at zero
let's say and then they start hCG um the
sperm count's going to start going back
up after you take it just the amount of
uh recovery period is going to vary
considerably personto person. Some they
might reach that baseline amount within
3 months. Um others maybe it'll take
longer. But I I think it's reasonable to
look at starting it at least 8 weeks
prior to trying to conceive to give
yourself that leeway of um you know
you're not going to just make 100
million sperm overnight. So it's it is
going to take some time